<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles, to be enquired of vvithin the dioces of London, in the third generall visitation of the reuerend Father in God, Richard, Bishop of London. Holden in the yeere of our Lord God 1604. In the second yeere of the raigne of our most gratious Soueraigne Lord Iames, by the grace of God of England, Fraunce, and Ireland, king, defender of the fayth; and of Scotland the thirtie eight, &amp;c..</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of London. Bishop (1597-1604 : Bancroft)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07647</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 180867084</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10255</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S92374</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">180867084</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 180867084</idno>
            <idno type="VID">191723</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07647)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 191723)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2284:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles, to be enquired of vvithin the dioces of London, in the third generall visitation of the reuerend Father in God, Richard, Bishop of London. Holden in the yeere of our Lord God 1604. In the second yeere of the raigne of our most gratious Soueraigne Lord Iames, by the grace of God of England, Fraunce, and Ireland, king, defender of the fayth; and of Scotland the thirtie eight, &amp;c..</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of London. Bishop (1597-1604 : Bancroft)</author>
                  <author>Bancroft, Richard, 1544-1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for Clement Knight.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's device (McK. 188 [beta]) on t.p.; initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ C².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England. --  Diocese of London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:191723:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES, To be enquired of vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Dioces of London, in the third generall Viſitation of the reuerend Father in God, <hi>Richard</hi> Biſhop of London.</p>
            <p>HOLDEN In the yeere of our Lord God 1604. In the ſecond yeere of the raigne of our moſt gratious Soueraigne Lord <hi>IAMES,</hi> by the grace of God of <hi>England, Fraunce, and Ireland, King,</hi> defender of the fayth; and of Scotland the thirtie eight, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London for Clement Knight. 1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb facs="tcp:191723:2"/>
            <head>A Branch of the Statute made in the firſt yeere of the raigne of our late Soueraigne Lady Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> intituled, <hi>An Act for the vniformitie of Common Prayer and ſeruice in the Church.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat from and after the feaſt of the Natiuitie of <hi>St. Iohn Baptiſt</hi> next comming, all and euery perſon &amp; perſons inhabiting within this Realme, or any other the Queenes maieſties dominions, ſhall diligently and faythfully (hauing no law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or reaſonable excuſe to be abſent) indeuour themſelues to reſort to their pariſh Church or Chappell accuſtomed, or vppon reaſonable let thereof to ſome vſuall place where common prayer and ſuch like ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God ſhall be vſed in ſuch time of let, vpon euery Sunday and other dayes, ordayned and vſed to be kept as Holy dayes, and then and there to abide orderly and ſoberly during the time of common prayer, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or other ſeruice of God there to be vſed and miniſtred, vpon paine of puniſhment by the Cenſures of the Church. And alſo vpon paine that euery perſon ſo offending, ſhall forfeite for euery ſuch offence twelue pence, to be leuied by the Church-wardens of the parish where ſuch offence shall be done, to the vſe of the poore of the ſame parish, of the goodes, landes, and tenementes of ſuch offender by way of diſtreſse. And for due executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on heereof, the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, the Lordes temparall, and all the commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, doth in Gods name earneſtly require and charge all the Archbishops, Bishops, and other Ordinaries, that they shall indeuour themſelues to the vttirmoſt of their knowledge, that the true and due execution hereof may be had throughout their Dioceſſe and charges, as they will anſwere before God for ſuch euils and plagues, wherewith almightie God may iuſtly puniſh his people for neglecting this good and holſome Lawe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:191723:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The tenour of the Othe miniſtred to the <hi>Churchwardens and Swornemen.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>YOu wall ſweare, that all affection, fauour, hatred, hope of rewarde and gaine, or feare of diſpleaſure, or mallice ſet aſide, you ſhall vpon due conſideration of the Articles giuen you in charge, preſent all and euery ſuch perſon of or within your pariſh, as hath committed any offence or fault, or made any default mentioned in theſe, or any of theſe Articles, or which are vehemently ſuſpected, or otherwiſe defamed of any ſuch offence, fault, or default: wherein you ſhall deale vprightly and according to trueth: neither of malice preſenting any contrary to trueth, nor of corrupt affection ſparing to preſent any, and ſo conceale the trueth, hauing in this action God before your eyes, with an earneſt zeale to maintaine trueth, and to ſuppreſſe vice. So helpe you God and the contentes of this Booke.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="charge">
            <head>The Charge of the Churchwardens and Swornemen, ſet downe for the better performance of their dueties, <hi>and diſcharge of their Othes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THey are ſtraightly charged to heare all theſe Articles read ouer to them, and diligently to conſider and inquire thereof, and for that the time is ſo ſhort in this Viſitation, that they ſhall not be able to make a perfect anſwere vnto all them; and that notwithſtanding there are many notorious faultes preſently worthy of preſentment and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, they are charged after their returne home, that together with their Miniſter they do read ouer all theſe Articles diſtinctly and leaſurely, to the end they may conſider of euery perticuler Article, and of the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in them conteined, as of ſuch perſons in their pariſh as ſhalbe noted to offende in any of them: and after that, to aſſemble themſelues in ſome conuenient time together and to make their Bill, anſwering euery Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle by it ſelfe, before the feaſt of <hi>St. Martin</hi> next enſuing, being the 10 day of Nouember: which Bill ſhall be ſigned with the hand of the Miniſter and of all the Church-wardens and Side-men, and ſhall for their better eaſe be brought by one of the Church-wardens vpon the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> day of Nouember next, vnto the Church of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> where for the ſauing of their trauell and charges vp to London, the Iudge and the Regiſter will be readie to receiue them.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:191723:3"/>
            <head>Articles to be enqired of vvithin the Dioces of London in this Viſitation holden in the yeere of our Lord God. 1604.</head>
            <div type="articles">
               <head>Articles concerning the Clergie.</head>
               <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether is Common prayer read by your Miniſter in your Church or Chappel diſtinctly and reuerently vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon all Sundayes and Holy dayes, and in ſuch order as is ſet foorth by the Lawes of this Realme in the booke of Common prayer, without any kind of alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, omitting or adding any thing, and at due and conuenient houres?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether doth your Miniſter vpon Wedneſdayes &amp; Frydayes (not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Holy dayes) read in your Church or Chappell, publikely the Letanie and other prayers appoynted in the ſaid booke for thoſe dayes: and whether doth he read the Commination againſt ſinners, in ſuch order and forme as it is there alſo preſcribed?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, in the adminiſtration of the Lordes Supper, or of Baptiſme, when he ſolemnizeth Matrimonie, bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth the dead, churcheth women, &amp;c. vſe the formes and prayers preſcribed in the Communion booke, without omitting or altering any part of them, and without any of his owne additions?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, read publike prayer &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the Sacramentes ordinarily himſelfe, vſing ſuch rites and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies as are preſcribed in the booke of Common prayer: as namely whether doth he kneele at the receiuing of the holy Communion, and adminiſter the ſame to none but to ſuch as do kneele at the receiuing therof: make the ſigne of the Croſſe vpon the childes forehead in the adminiſtration of Baptiſme: Baptiſe any without Godfathers and Godmothers: vſe the Ring in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: and generally whether doth he in the diſcharging of al theſe dueties, and when he readeth Common prayer eyther vpon Sundayes, Holy dayes, Wedneſdayes and Frydayes weare a Surplice?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Whether doth your Miniſter vpon Sundayes at morning prayer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto the pariſhioners what Holydayes and Faſting dayes are appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be kept the weeke following; whereby they may be put in minde to prepare themſelues, and to repaire to the Church to publike prayer, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the lawes of the Realme?</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb facs="tcp:191723:3"/>6 Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, or either of them reiect at any time thoſe women (being married) which do come to church to giue God thankes after their childbirth, or refuſe or neglect to viſit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſicke, or to burie the dead, according to their duties preſcribed in the booke of common prayer?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Whether doth your miniſter in the Rogation dayes of proceſſion vſe the perambulation of the circuite of your pariſh, appoynted by Law: and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he in the ſayd perambulation moone the people to giue thankes to God in the beholding of his benefites, for the increaſe and aboundance of his fruites vpon the face of the earth: and ſing or ſay the two Pſalmes, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>Prayſe the Lord O my ſoule. &amp;c.</hi> with the Letanie &amp; ſuffrages there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto belonging: and at certaine conuenient places reade the Homily of thankſgiuing to God, alreadie deuiſed, and diuided into foure partes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out addition of any ſuperſtitious ceremonie heretofore vſed?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Whether doth any man, being neither Miniſter nor Deacon, read com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer openly in your Church or Chappel, or adminiſter the ſacrament of baptiſme, or ſolemnize matrimony, or take vpon him to practiſe any other miniſteriall dutie in the church, that is preſcribed to be executed particularly by ſuch as are either miniſters or Deacons; &amp; what is his name that ſo doth?</p>
               <p n="9">9 Whether is your Parſon or Vicar a Preacher, licenſed to preach by lawfull authoritie according to Law? if he be, how many Sermons doth he preach yeerely: if he be not, how many doth he procure to be preached by others: who hath preached them, and whether were they Preachers lycen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as is before expreſſed?</p>
               <p n="10">10 Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, euery Sunday &amp; Holy day when there is no Sermon, read diſtinctly and plainely ſome part of the Homilies preſcribed and ſet foorth by Law.</p>
               <p n="11">11 Whether doth the Parſon, Vicar, or Farmour of the Benefice in your pariſh cauſe or ſuffer any Curate or Miniſter, either to read ſeruice, &amp;c. or to preach, before he the ſaid Curate (being no preacher) be examined &amp; admitted by the Ordinarie in writing: and before he the ſaid Curate being a preacher be thereunto admitted according to Law, and before they ſhew their ſayd ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall licences vnto the Churchwardens?</p>
               <p n="12">12 Whether doth your Preacher in his prayer which he maketh at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traunce into his Sermon, vſe at all times the prayer for his Maieſtie, for our geacious Queene, the Prince, and all the reſt of the royall progenie, with his whole title; as, King of England, Scotland, Fraunce, and Ireland, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the fayth, &amp;c. and of all cauſes, and ouer all perſons within his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe dominions, as well eccleſiaſticall as temporall, next and immediatly
<pb facs="tcp:191723:4"/>
vnder God, ſupreme gouernor. And whether doth he in like manner then pray for the Archbiſhops and Biſhops, as by law is alſo appoynted?</p>
               <p n="13">13 Whether your Miniſter doth ſerue two Cures in one day?</p>
               <p n="14">14 Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, euery Sunday and Holy day openly in the Church earneſtly call for, heare, and inſtruct all the Children, Apprentiſes, and Seruants of both ſexes, that be of conuenient age within your Pariſh, or at the leaſt ſo many of them by courſe as the time will ſerue, and as he may well heare &amp; inſtruct one houre at the leaſt, before or after euening prayer, in the ten Commandements, the Articles of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, and the Lords prayer: and diligently examine &amp; teach them the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, as it is now allowed and ſet foorth in the booke of Common prayer?</p>
               <p n="15">15 Whether is there any man in your pariſh, being neither your Parſon, Vicar, nor Curate, that taketh vpon him to preach or read Lectures eyther in priuate houſes, or publikely in your church or chappell, who is not licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to preach or read there: or who doth not once a yeere at the leaſt admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the Sacraments in your ſayd Church or Chappell, where he ſo prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth or readeth, according to the booke.</p>
               <p n="16">16 Whether your Miniſter hath or doth receiue to the holy Communion any perſons which be not of his owne pariſh, without teſtimonie from the Miniſter of the place where they dwell, what they be, that it may appeare that they be not perſons excommunicate, or otherwiſe infamous.</p>
               <p n="17">17 Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, reiect any from the holy Communion, who is not by publique fame, or by preſentment of the Church-wardens detected for a notorious Fornicator, Adulterer, or other wicked lyuer, or diſturber of his neighbours by whom publique offence is giuen: and whether he receiue any ſuch perſon ſo infamed or preſented, to the holy Communion before publique penaunce inioyned by his Ordinarie be by him firſt performed, to the ſatisfaction of the Congregation according to the Law in that caſe prouided?</p>
               <p n="18">18 Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, or any other Miniſter or Preacher, baptiſe in your Pariſh-church or Chappell, any Infants, not in the Font according to the antient cuſtome, but in a Baſon, and vrge the parentes of the ſayd Infant to be preſent, in place of Godfathers for their children?</p>
               <p n="19">19 Whether doth your Parſon Vicar, or Curate, once euery quarter of the yeere read his Maieſties Iniunctions openly and deliberately before his pariſhioners at one time or at two ſeuerall times in one day, according as in the ſayd Iniunctions it is preſcribed?</p>
               <p n="20">
                  <pb facs="tcp:191723:4"/>20 Whether hath your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, or any other Miniſter, publiquely or priuately preached, declared, or ſpoken any thing in your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in derogation of the booke of Common-prayer, which is ſet foorth by the lawes of this Realme, diſprayſing, or deprauing the ſame, or any thing therein contayned; or againſt the preſent eſtate of the Eccleſiaſticall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, eſtabliſhed by the ſame authoritie, or agaynſt any office, function, or part thereof, affirming the ſame to be vnlawfull?</p>
               <p n="21">21 Whether hath your Parſon or Vicar, more Benefices then one? yf he hath not, whether is he reſident vpon that one? yf he be not reſident, where doth he remayne? and whether doth he leaue a ſufficient Miniſter and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher to ſupply his abſence, allowyng ſomething yeerely towardes the reliefe of the poore? and what doth he ſo allow?</p>
               <p n="22">22 Whether is your Parſon or Vicar, who hath two Benefices within this Dioces; or one Benefice in this Dioces, &amp; an other foorth of the ſame, reſident one halfe of the yeere on one of them, and the other halfe yeere, or the greater part thereof vpon his other Benefice: and whether doth he leaue the Benefice in your paryſh prouided of a ſufficient Preacher to ſerue it: and hath an eſpecial care of ſome conuenient hoſpitality to be kept in his abſence according to his ability, and the proportion of that lyuing?</p>
               <p n="23">23 Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, keepe a iuſt and perfect note of all ſuch as do communicate in your pariſh, and do not rather, regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their priuate gayne, receiue their offeringes at Eaſter, delyuer them Tokens, enter them into their booke, and ſo certifie as communicantes thoſe who neuer receiued?</p>
               <p n="24">24 Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, keepe any man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in their houſes, that are ſuſpected to be eyther of euill religion, or of bad life: or whether be they or any of them incontinent perſons themſelues, or giuen to drunkennes, or to be haunters of tauerns, alehouſes, or ſuſpected places, common Dicers, Carders, Tableplayers, Swearers, Dauncers, or otherwiſe ſuſpected perſons of any notorious crime, or light and vnſeeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly behauiour, or giue euill example of lyfe, or vſe diſordered or vnſeemely apparrell, eyther in cullours, guardes, or light faſhion?</p>
               <p n="25">25 Whether there be any Miniſters or Prieſtes within your pariſh, which liue idlely without any care, neyther ſeruing in any place, nor hauing any place of reading or preaching, and ſo become offenſiue to their calling, and what be their names who ſo lyue, and how long haue they been with you?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <pb facs="tcp:191723:5"/>
               <head>Articles concerning the Church.</head>
               <p n="1">1 WHether haue you in your pariſh Churches and Chappels all things neceſſarie and requiſite for Common prayer and adminiſtration of the Sacramentes, eſpecially the booke of Common prayer with the new Kalender, two Pſalters (all ſet foorth by his Maieſties eſpeciall commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement and Proclamation onely to be vſed, printed by his Highneſſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the which you were by your Archdeacons commaunded from mee, to haue bought before Whitſontide laſt,) the Engliſh Bible in the largeſt vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume of the edition ſet foorth by the Biſhops, and lately imprinted by the Kinges Printer; the Table of the ten Commaundements, a conuenient Pulpit well placed, a comely and decent Table ſtanding vpon a frame for the holy Communion, with a faire Linnen cloth to lay vpon the ſame, and ſome couering of Silke, Buckram, or other ſuch like for the cleane keeping thereof; a faire and comely communion Cuppe of Siluer, and a couer of Siluer for the ſame, which may ſerue alſo for the miniſtration of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion Bread, a decent large Surples with fleeues, and a ſtrong Cheſt or Boxe for the almes of the poore, with three lockes and keyes to the ſame, and all other thinges neceſſarie in and to the premiſſes?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether there haue growne in your Church ſince the laſt Viſitation in the yeere 1601. any contention betwixt any of the pariſhioners, touching the placing or diſplacing of any in any ſeate or pew in the Church: and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there hath been any Pew buylded ſince the foreſayd yeere 1601. in any your Churches, without the expreſſe leaue and conſent firſt had of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie of the Dioces, and by whom haue any ſuch been built.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether is your Church or Chappell, and the Chauncell well and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently repaired and kept without abuſe of any thing: whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, or the Proprietarie or Farmer of your Parſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage or Vicarage in your pariſh keepe the Parſonage or Vicarage houſe with all other the edifices thereunto appertaining in good and ſufficient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations: and whether is your Church-yard well fenced and cleanly kept without any lapſtall or other annoyances,</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether your Church be a Parſonage or a Vicarage preſentatiue or bonatiue, or otherwiſe ſerued by a Curate: whether did they euer heereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heare or know that it was a Parſonage or Vicarage, and how came it to be decayed from being preſentatiue, to be in the ſtate it now is, and when was it firſt decayed, from being a benefice preſentatiue, as you remember.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb facs="tcp:191723:5"/>5 Whether your Foules or Baptiſteries be remooued from the place where they were wont to ſtand, towardes the lower end of the Church: or whether any perſons, leauing the vſe of them, do chriſten or baptiſe in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or other veſſels, not accuſtomably vſed in the Church before time: or do vſe any kind of Lauor with a remooueable Baſon, or haue taken downe the old and vſuall Font heretofore vſed in your periſh?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Whether is there in your Pariſh a ſufficient Regiſter booke of Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of marriages, chriſtnings, and burials, prouided at the charge of the Pariſh: whether are all the names of thoſe that haue been either chriſtened, married, or buried, ſince the beginning of her lace Maieſties raigne newly written into the ſayd Parchment booke? Whether doth the Miniſter euery Sunday read the names publikely of thoſe that were either chriſtned, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, or buried the weeke before? Whether haue you a publike Cheſt with three lockes, for the Miniſter and the two Church-wardens to keepe the ſayd Booke in: and whether haue you brought a tranſcript of all the names of ſuch as haue been chriſtned, marryed, and buried this laſt yeere into <hi>M. Blackwell</hi> my Regiſter his office, as you are bound to do euery yeere here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, within a month after the Feaſt of Eaſter, by the Conſtitutions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <head>Articles concerning Eccleſiaſticall Officers.</head>
               <p n="1">1 WHether the Chancelor, Archdeacon, Commiſſarie, Officiall, or any other vſing Eccleſiaſtical Iuriſdiction in this Dioces, their Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters or Actuaries, Apparators, or Summoners, haue at any time winked at and ſuffered any adulterers, fornicators, inceſts, or other faultes or offences preſented vnto them, to paſſe and remaine vnpuniſhed, and vncorrected for mony, rewardes, bribes, pleaſure, friendſhip, or any other partiall reſpect?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether doth the Chancellor, Commiſſaries, Archdeacons, or any other Officials, heare any matters of office, or correction priuately in their cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers without the preſence of the ſworne Regiſter or his deputie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or do diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge any mans penance, for money, without the conſent of the L. Biſhop, according to the conſtitutions; or doe ſende any writing vnder their owne hands to your Church, without the Regiſters preſence at the doing of it, eyther for marryage of any couples, or for ending or ordering of any matter or penance?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether the Chauncelor, Officiall, or Commiſſarie, haue cauſed for, or cauſed the Church-wardens to make, bring, or to pay for any more Billes of preſentment, then once in euery yeere; or do call for their quarter Billes, or make the Church-wardens pay for them?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <pb facs="tcp:191723:6"/>
               <head>Articles concerning Schoolemaiſters.</head>
               <p n="1">1 WWhether the Schoolemaiſter or Schoolemaiſters within your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh openly or priuately in any Noble or Gentlemans houſe, or in any other place, be of good and ſinceere religion, life, and conuerſation, and be diligent in teaching and bringing vp of youth: and whether they haue been examined, allowed, and licenſed for Schoolemaiſters by the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in that behalfe?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether your Schoolemaiſter or Schoolemaiſters do themſelues re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the holy Communion as often as they ought to do: and whether do all their Schollers, which be of age ſufficient, and of copacitie by inſtruction, to receiue the Lords Supper, come to the Communion either in your Church or where their Parents dwell once euery yeere, and be diligent to heare Common prayer?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether your Schoolemaſter or Schoolemaſters do orderly on Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes with their Schollers, come to the Church of their pariſh where they teach, and there ſee their Schollers placed in ſome conuenient place, ſo as they do not diſquiet the miniſter or pariſh in time of diuine ſeruice, but may exerciſe themſelues godly in reading and hearing the Seruice &amp; Sermons, and in anſwering with the congregation in reading of publike prayer?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether the Schoolemaiſter or Schoolemaiſters either priuate or publike do teach their Schollers the Catechiſme authorized by publike au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, at the leaſt once euery weeke, and do inſtruct and examine them in the ſame: or do teach any other Catechiſme, and what Catechiſme it is that they ſo do teach?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Whether your Schoolemaiſter or Schoolemaiſters, or any of them be knowne or ſuſpected to read vnto their Schollers priuately any vnlawfull Bookes: or priuately to inſtruct them in their young yeeres either in pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſuperſtition, or diſobedience, or contempt to his Maieſtie and his lawes Eccleſiaſticall by publike authoritie allowed?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Whether your Schoolemaiſter or Schoolemaiſters, or any of them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of Catechiſing their Schollers, which is a moſt godly order, carefully by them to be obſerued, do keepe lectures, readinges, or expoſition in diuinitie in their houſes, hauing repaire vnto them of people not being of their owne family and houſehould?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Whether the Schoolemaiſter or Schoolemaiſters within your pariſh, do teach his or their Schollers any other Grammer then that which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the Kinges Grammer, ſet foorth by the authoritie of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <pb facs="tcp:191723:6"/>
               <head>Articles concerning the Pariſhioners and others of the Laitie.</head>
               <p n="1">1 WHether all Houſeholders in your pariſh cauſe their children, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and apprentiſes, both mankind &amp; womankind, being aboue ſeuen yeeres of age, and vnder twentie, which haue not learned the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, to come to the Church on Sundayes and Holy dayes at the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted for Cetechiſing, and there diligently and obediently to heare, and what be the names of thoſe that do not cauſe their children, ſeruants, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiſes ſo to come to the Church to be inſtructed and examined?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether the Churchwardens do delyuer to the Archdeacon at his Viſitation, a note of all thoſe who do not ſende their children and ſeruantes to be catechized?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether any do worke, or keepe any ſhoppe open vpon Saboth dayes, or vpon any Holy dayes appoynted by the lawes of this Realme to be kepe Holy day, or vſe any worke or labour, or open ſhew of their wares in any of thoſe dayes?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether you your ſelues, or the Churchwardens in the yeeres before you, haue ſuffered any vnmarryed women being begotten with child, to goe out of your pariſh before ſhe hath by you or them been preſented to your Ordinarie: or any man defamed of whoredome, to depart vnpuniſhed, vpon direction appoynted by the Ordinarie? And foorth of whoſe houſes haue they gone away with child vnpuniſhed, and what be the names of ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marryed women which haue been deliuered within your pariſh this three yeeres laſt paſt, haue gone away without doing of penance?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Whether the pariſh Clarke be appoynted according to the law, by the Parſon or Vicar of the pariſh, with the allowance of the Ordinarie: and whether he be not obedient to the Parſon, Vicar, or Curate: and whether he be able to read, and whether he keepe the Bookes and Ornaments of the Church faire and cleane, and cauſe the Church, and Quire, the Communion Table and the Font, to be kept cleane and decent againſt the Seruice time, the Communion, Sermon, and Baptiſme?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Whether there be any perſon or perſons eccleſiaſticall or temporall, within your pariſh or elſe wheſe within this Dioces, that haue retayned and kept in their cuſtody, or that read, ſell, vtter, diſperſe, carry, or deliuer to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers any Engliſh Bookes or Libels, ſet forth either on this ſide or beyond the Seas, by Papiſtes or Sectaries againſt the Kings ſupremacie in cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes eccleſiaſticall, or againſt true Religon and Catholike doctrine now pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely
<pb facs="tcp:191723:7"/>
profeſſed in this Church, or the gouernment or diſcipline of the Church of England, now within this Realme receiued and eſtabliſhed by common authoritie, and what their names and ſurnames are?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Whether there be any in your pariſh who are noted, knowne, or ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to conceale or keepe hidden in their houſes any Maſſe bookes, porteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, breuiaries, or other bookes of popery and ſuperſtition, or any Challices Copes, Veſtments, Albs, or other ornaments of ſuperſtition, vncancelled or vndefaced, which it is to be coniectured they do keep for a day, as they cal it?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Whether there be in your pariſh any popiſh or ſectary recuſant or recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, which for any cauſe whatſoeuer, forbeare to come to Church to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer, or to heare Gods word preached, pretending it vnlawfull to come to our aſſemblies, as the Church of England now ſtandeth, eſtabliſhed by his Maieſties authoritie, and what their ſeuerall name or names are, and how long they haue been recuſants?</p>
               <p n="9">9 Whether any do refuſe to receiue the holy Communion at their owne Miniſters handes, either becauſe he is not a Preacher, or becauſe he duly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth the order of miniſtration appoynted by the booke, and who they be that do go from their owne pariſh, to receiue at any other miniſters hands?</p>
               <p n="10">10 Whether any of your pariſhioners hauing a Preacher to their Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, do abſent themſelues from his Sermons, and reſort to any other place to heare other preachers?</p>
               <p n="11">11 Whether all the people of your pariſh aboue 16. yeeres of age, and eſpecially houſeholders, hauing no lawfull excuſe to be abſent, doe reſort with their ſeruantes and children to their pariſh Church or Chappell on the Holy dayes, and on the Sundayes to morning and euening prayer, and who they be that either negligently or wilfully abſent themſelues, or do vnreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently behaue themſelues in the Church, or vſe any gaming or paſtime a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade or in any houſe, or ſitte in the ſtreete or Church-yard, or in any ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, or alehouſe, vpon the Sunday, or Holyday, in the time of Common prayer, Sermon, or reading of the Homilies, or any of them, either before or after noone?</p>
               <p n="12">12 Whether the forfeyture of xii. pence for euery time of abſence from the Church vpon euery Sunday and Holyday, appoynted by a Statute made in the firſt yeere of the late Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> raigne, to be leuied and taken according to the ſame Statute (the tenor whereof is ſette downe in the beginning of this Booke) by the Churchwardens of euery perſon that offendeth, and by them be put to the vſe of the poore of the pariſh if it be not ſo le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed, by whoſe fault it is?</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <pb facs="tcp:191723:7"/>13 Whether there be any Inkeepers, Alewiues, Victuallers, or Tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, that ſuffer or do admitte any perſon or perſons in their houſes to eate, drinke, or play at Dice, Cardes, Tables, Bowles, or ſuch like games, in the time of Common prayer or Sermon, on the Sundayes or Holydayes: or any Butchers, or other that commonly vſe to ſell meate or other thinges in the time of common prayer, preaching, or reading of Homilies? and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in any Faires or common Markets fallyng vpon the Sundayes, there be ſhewing of any wares before morning prayer be done: and whether any markets and ſelling of wares be vſed or ſuffered in any Church-yards on the Sabboth day by common Packmen or Pedlers going about, or any Butchers?</p>
               <p n="14">14 Whether the Church-wardens of the laſt yeere, hath giuen to the Parſon or Vicar and the pariſh, a iuſt account of the Church goodes that were committed to their charge, according to the cuſtome that hath been afore time vſed: and what Church goodes they or any other haue ſold, and to whom, and whether to the profite of your Church or no: and what hath been done with the mony thereof comming?</p>
               <p n="15">15 Whether the Church-wardens and Swornmen, ſince the fourth day of Auguſt 1601. haue of any priuate corrupt affection concealed any crime or other diſorder in their time done in your pariſh, and haue not preſented the ſame to the Biſhop, Chauncelor, Archdeacon, Commiſſarie, or ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as had authoritie to reforme the ſame? and whether they or any of them, at any ſuch time as they ſhould haue been at diuine ſeruice on Sundayes and Holy dayes, and ſhould there haue obſerued others that were abſent, haue beene away themſelues, at home, or in ſome Tauerne or Alehouſe, or elſe about ſome worldly buſineſſe, or at bowles, cardes, tables, dice, or other gaming, without regard of their office and duetie in that behalfe?</p>
               <p n="16">16 Whether your Miniſter and you the Church-wardens, or any other in your pariſh haue in your regeſtries made any orders, or do vſe to call any parties before you for any cauſe to be ordered by the Eccleſiaſticall lawes, and ſo do vſe a kind of Preſbiterie or cenſuring ouer your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures, vnder pretence of your veſtrie meetings?</p>
               <p n="17">17 Whether any of your pariſh, being of conuenient age, haue not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the holy Communion thrice this laſt yeere at the leaſt, and namely at Eaſter laſt, or thereaboutes for once, and what their names are, or which at their receiuing haue not ſignified the ſame before to your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, that he might conueniently examine them: and who haue refuſed to come to him to be examined?</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <pb facs="tcp:191723:8"/>18 Whether there be any in your pariſh that doth adminiſter the goodes of thoſe that be dead without lawfull authoritie; or any that ſuppreſſe the laſt will of the dead, or any Executors that haue not fulfilled their teſtators laſt will, in paying of legacies giuen to the Church, or to other good and godly vſes; as to the reliefe of pouerty, to Orphanes, poore Schollers, poore Maydens marriages, High-wayes, and ſuch like, and by whom are they ſo deteyned?</p>
               <p n="19">19 Whether there be any in your pariſh, that ſince the fourth of Auguſt 1601. hath or doth offend contrary to the Statute made in the ſeauen and thirtieth yeere of the raigne of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, for the reformation of Vſurie, and reuiued by an Act made in the thirteenth yeere of the raigne of our late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> taking aboue the rate of ten poundes for the lending of an hundred poundes by the yeere: and what be the names of ſuch offenders?</p>
               <p n="20">20 Whether hath your Miniſter, or any of the pariſh, without the conſent or priuitie of the Ordinarie, cauſed any to do penance, or be puniſhed eyther openly or otherwiſe, for any crime puniſhable by the Eccleſiaſticall lawes onely, and what be the names of the parties that haue been ſo puniſhed, and in what manner?</p>
               <p n="21">21 Whether there be any amongſt you that do vſe Sorcerie or Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft puniſhable by the Eccleſiaſticall lawes, or that be ſuſpected of the ſame: and whether any vſe any Charmes or vnlawfull Prayers: and whether any do reſort to any ſuch for helpe and councell, and what be the names, both of ſuch as vſe it, and of ſuch as reſort to them for helpe?</p>
               <p n="22">22 Whether any couples that be marryed in priuate houſes within theſe three yeeres laſt paſt, haue been knowne, or ſuſpected to haue been marryed by any popiſh Prieſt or otherwiſe, after any other order then is appoynted by the Church of England?</p>
               <p n="23">23 Whether there be among you any blaſphemers of the name of God, great or often ſwearers, adulterers, fornicators, harlots, or whoremaſters, inceſtuous perſons, bawdes, or receiuers of naughtie and incontinent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or harborers of women with child which be vnmarryed, conueying or ſuffering them to go away before they do any penance: or any that be vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently ſuſpected of any ſuch faultes, or that be not of good name and fame touching ſuch crimes and faultes of drunkards, or ribawdes: or any that be malitious, contentious, or vncharitable perſons, raylers, ſcoulders, or ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of diſcord betweene nighbours, and eſpecially raylers againſt miniſters and againſt their marryage, and what be all their ſeuerall names?</p>
               <p n="24">
                  <pb facs="tcp:191723:8"/>24 Whether there be any in theſe partes, that haue been marryed within the degrees of affinitie or conſanguinitie, by the lawes of God forbidden: or any that being diuorced or ſeperated for the ſame, do yet notwithſtanding cohabite and keepe company ſtill together: or any that being marryed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thoſe degrees, haue vnlawfully forſaken their wiues or huſbandes, and marryed others: Any that being diuorced or ſeparated a ſunder, haue mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed againe: any that haue marryed without Banes three ſeuerall Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes or Holy dayes ſolemnely aſked, &amp; without lawfull licenſe thereunto: or any couples married that liue not together, but ſlaunderouſly liue apart?</p>
               <p n="25">25 Whether there be any in your pariſh who will come to heare the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, but will not come to the publike prayer appoynted by the booke of Common prayer, making a ſchiſme or diuiſion (as it were) betweene the vſe of publike prayer and preaching? And whether there be any, who being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at publike prayer, do not deuoutly and humbly kneele vpon their knees, at ſuch times as by the Booke of common prayer they are appoynted; to wit, when they make a generall confeſſion of their ſinnes: when all prayers and Collects are read: in the time of the Lettenie: when the tenne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements are read, and at their receiuing of the holy Communion, &amp;c. and what are their names that haue at any time ſhewed themſelues vndueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vnreuerent in this behalfe?</p>
               <p n="26">26 Whether the Miniſter and Church-wardens haue ſuffered any Lord of Miſ-rule, or Summer lord or ladyes, or any diſguiſed perſons: any play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or May-games, or any Moris-dauncers at any time to come vnreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently into the Church or Church yard, and there to daunce or play, or ſhew them ſelues diſguiſed in the time of Common prayer, and what they be that commit ſuch diſorder, or that accompanied or maintayned them: or any Playes to be played in the Church?</p>
               <p n="27">27 Whether there be any marryed women or others within your Pariſh, which after chyldbirth, refuſe or contemne to come to the Church to giue God thankes for their deliuery, and to haue the prayers publikely appoynted in that behalfe by the booke of common prayer?</p>
               <p n="28">28 Whether any within your Pariſh do reſort vnto Barnes, Fieldes, Woodes, priuate Houſes, or to any extraordinay expoſition of Scriptures, or conferences together, or that be drawers or perſwaders of others to any ſuch ſciſmaticall conuenticles.</p>
               <p n="29">29 Whether any do keepe their chyldren vnbaptized longer then is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueuient, vnleſſe it be for ſickneſſe of the child, or other vrgent occaſion: And
<pb facs="tcp:191723:9"/>
whether any doe carry their children from the Pariſh they are borne in, to other Pariſhes to be bapitzed, and ſo refuſe their owne Pariſh: or do bring ſtrange miniſters into their owne houſes to baptize their children priuatly, according to their owne fantaſies;</p>
               <p n="30">30 Whether any notorious Recuſant, who obſtinately refuſeth to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker with the Church of England in publike prayer, and hearing of the word of God preached, who is for his diſobedience and contempt excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, and dyeth excommunicate, be buryed in Chriſtian buriall, not hauing before his death ſought to be abſolued, and teſtified the ſame his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to ſome honeſt and diſcreete man, who ſhall vpon his oath ſignifie to the Biſhop of the Dioces, whereby his Lordſhip may giue order to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie, before whom he was excommunicate for his abſolution.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <p>AT the deliuerie of your Bill of preſentment, at the time and place aboue ſet downe, you are likewiſe in the ſayd Bill, to ſet downe the names of all ſuch as haue been buried at any time ſince the ſeuenth of Auguſt 1604. being men, maydes, or widdowes: and likewiſe the names of ſuch as haue been married by any Licenſe ſince that time, and out of what Court they haue been graunted, ſince the ſayd ſeuenth of Auguſt.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:191723:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
